Kurmanji: فقيران أو رأس الأسود قرية سورية جميلة تقع غرب
مدينة عفرين في ريف حلب الشمالي بثمانية كيلومترات وتتبع لها.
English Translation: Faqiran, or Ras Al-Aswad, is a
beautiful Syrian village located eight kilometers west of
the city of Afrin in the northern countryside of Aleppo, and
is administratively part of it.
Kurmanji: كما أنها تقع على بعد خمسة عشر كيلومتراً شمال شرق
مدينة جنديرس التابعة لعفرين.
English Translation: It is also located 15 kilometers
northeast of the town of Jindires, which belongs to Afrin.
Kurmanji: وتبعد عن مدينة حلب خمسة وسبعين كيلومتراً باتجاه
الشمال الغربي.
English Translation: And it is 75 kilometers northwest of
the city of Aleppo.
Kurmanji: وقد بنيت القرية على هضبة متجهة نحو الجنوب في سهل
جوم في ريف حلب الشمالي.
English Translation: The village was built on a south-facing
plateau in the Joum plain in the northern countryside of
Aleppo.
Kurmanji: سكانها الأصليين من الأكراد السوريين الإيزيديين.
English Translation: Its original inhabitants are Syrian
Kurdish Yazidis.
Kurmanji: أما مجموع سكانها الحاليين فيبلغ حوالي سبعمئة نسمة
من السكان الأصليين إضافة إلى عوائل سورية مهجرة من حمص ودرعا
وأرياف حلب الشمالي والغربي.
English Translation: As for its current total population, it
is around 700 people, comprising original inhabitants in
addition to displaced Syrian families from Homs, Daraa, and
the northern and western countrysides of Aleppo.
Kurmanji: يوجد غرب القرية وادٍ كانت تجري فيه مياه الينابيع
إضافة إلى بئر ماء روماني قديم.
English Translation: To the west of the village, there is a
valley where spring waters used to flow, in addition to an
old Roman water well.
Kurmanji: هاجر معظم أبنائها إلى أوروبا من أجل الدراسة
والعمل.
English Translation: Most of its young people have migrated
to Europe for study and work.
Kurmanji: يوجد في القرية معصرة زيتون ومدرسة ابتدائية.
English Translation: There is an olive press and a primary
school in the village.
Kurmanji: يمتاز أهلها بالطبيعة العاطفية والطبع العملي وهم من
ذوي الفطرة الطيبة.
English Translation: Its people are characterized by their
emotional nature and practical disposition, and they are of
good character.
Kurmanji: السلام عليكم.
English Translation: Peace be upon you.
Kurmanji: عليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
English Translation: And upon you be peace and the mercy of
Allah.
Kurmanji: أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: How are you?
English Translation: Welcome.
Kurmanji: الله يعافيك يا رب.
English Translation: May God give you health.
English Translation: May God give you health too.
Kurmanji: إيه من الضيعة، سكان الضيعة.
English Translation: Are you from the village here?
English Translation: Yes, from the village, residents of the
village.
Kurmanji: الله يكرمك، عم تقطعوا حطب؟
English Translation: May God bless you. Are you cutting
firewood?
Kurmanji: إيه والله طالعين عم نبيع لنا حطب، نشتري كم غرض
ونروح على البيت.
English Translation: Yes indeed, we are out to sell some
firewood, buy a few things, and go home.
Kurmanji: إيشو هذا الحطب؟
English Translation: What kind of firewood is this?
Kurmanji: حطب زيتون والله.
English Translation: It's olive firewood.
Kurmanji: شقد الطن اليوم؟ شقد الكيلو؟
English Translation: How much is a ton today? How much is a
kilo?
Kurmanji: الطن هلق بعناه بخمسين دولار.
English Translation: We just sold a ton for 50 dollars.
Kurmanji: خمسين دولار؟ لأنه آخر موسم؟
English Translation: 50 dollars? Because it's the end of the
season?
Kurmanji: إيه طبعا آخر موسم.
English Translation: Yes, of course, it's the end of the
season.
Kurmanji: كان أغلى من هيك مو هيك؟
English Translation: It used to be more expensive than this,
right?
Kurmanji: إيه طبعا أول كان أغلى بس هلق الجو تغير وما في
شتاء.
English Translation: Yes, of course, earlier it was more
expensive, but now the weather has changed and there's no
winter.
Kurmanji: قديش هون أهالي الضيعة معتمدين على بيع الحطب؟
English Translation: How much do the people of the village
here rely on selling firewood?
Kurmanji: يعني شلون ما فهمت عليك السؤال؟
English Translation: I mean, how? I didn't understand your
question.
Kurmanji: يعني بيع الحطب، مصدر رزق لهم؟
English Translation: I mean, is selling firewood a source of
income for them?
Kurmanji: إيه طبعا، الأغلبية، هذا رزقنا، مصدر رزقنا هو.
English Translation: Yes, of course. For the majority, this
is our livelihood, it's our source of income.
Kurmanji: مصدر منيح يعني، نسبة كبيرة من السكان بيبيعوا حطب
وبيعيشوا منه؟
English Translation: A good source, I mean, a large
percentage of the residents sell firewood and make a living
from it?
Kurmanji: إيه والله في منه كثير، في منه مثلا ما بيبيعوا حطب
يعني، اللي عنده مثلا زاد، بيبيع، وإذا ما زاد بيعيفه.
English Translation: Yes, indeed, there are many. There are
some, for example, who don't sell firewood. Those who have a
surplus sell it, and if there's no surplus, they keep it.
Kurmanji: إيش بيشتغلوا غير بيع الحطب؟
English Translation: What do they work in besides selling
firewood?
Kurmanji: بالزيتون أكثر شيء.
English Translation: Mostly in olives.
Kurmanji: تمام، أكثر شيء عندكم زراعة بالزيتون؟
English Translation: Okay, you mostly have olive farming?
Kurmanji: إيه أكثر شيء زراعة بالزيتون عندنا.
English Translation: Yes, we mostly have olive farming here.
Kurmanji: غير الزيتون، عندكم أغنام، أبقار؟
English Translation: Besides olives, do you have sheep,
cows?
Kurmanji: لا غنم قليل عندنا، قليل.
English Translation: No, we have very few sheep, very few.
Kurmanji: يعني ما بتشتغلوا بالرعي، ما عندكم رعي؟
English Translation: So you don't work in herding, you don't
have grazing?
Kurmanji: لا ما في، واحد مثلا الضيعة كلها، عندي مثلا أخوي
عنده عشرتين ثلاثة.
English Translation: No, we don't. For example, in the whole
village, maybe my brother has twenty or thirty.
Kurmanji: يعني أكثر شيء عندنا مثلا زراعة الزيتون، نحن ما في
عندنا أراضي فاضية مثلا الأغنام مثلا يشتغلوا فيها يعني.
English Translation: Meaning, we mostly have olive farming.
We don't have empty lands where, for example, sheep herding
can be practiced.
Kurmanji: هلق في مرعى للأغنام؟
English Translation: Is there a pasture for sheep now?
Kurmanji: إيه طبعا، ما في قليل عندنا هنا، لكن الأكثرية
بيشتغل في الزيتون.
English Translation: Yes, of course, but it's very little
here. The majority work in olives.
Kurmanji: مصدر رزقهم الأساسي؟
English Translation: Their main source of income?
Kurmanji: أكثر شيء عندنا الزيتون، رزقنا الزيتون عندنا
بالمنطقة.
English Translation: Olives are our main thing. Our
livelihood is olives here in the region.
Kurmanji: إن شاء الله وضعكم منيح؟
English Translation: Hopefully your situation is good?
Kurmanji: الحمد لله رب العالمين، نشكر الله، الحمد لله.
English Translation: Praise be to Allah, Lord of the Worlds.
We thank God, praise be to Allah.
Kurmanji: الحمد لله، الله يقويكم، شكرا لك.
English Translation: Praise be to Allah. May God give you
strength. Thank you.
Kurmanji: يسلمك، الله يخليك، أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: May God keep you safe and protect you.
Welcome.
Kurmanji: السلام عليكم.
English Translation: Peace be upon you.
Kurmanji: شلونك؟
English Translation: How are you?
Kurmanji: الحمد لله.
English Translation: How is your health?
English Translation: Praise be to Allah.
Kurmanji: الله يعافيك.
English Translation: May God give you health.
English Translation: May God give you health too.
Kurmanji: نتعرف عليك؟
English Translation: May we know your name?
Kurmanji: أحمد الحمادي من ريف حلب الجنوبي.
English Translation: Ahmed Al-Hammadi, from the southern
countryside of Aleppo.
Kurmanji: أهلا وسهلا، ريف حلب الجنوبي، من وين بالضبط؟
English Translation: Welcome. From the southern countryside
of Aleppo, from where exactly?
Kurmanji: خان طومان.
English Translation: Khan Tuman.
Kurmanji: أهلا وسهلا فيك، هلق أنتم هون بضيعة فقيران، عم
تزرعوا، شو القصة؟
English Translation: Welcome. Now you are here in the
village of Faqiran, farming. What's the story?
Kurmanji: والله عم نشتغل أخي بالزراعة، أرض أخي بين الكروم،
مشان أخي يعني أحسن ما نقعد، وبشان نطالع قوت يومنا.
English Translation: Well, we are working in farming,
brother. Land between the vineyards, brother, so that
instead of sitting idle, we can earn our daily bread.
Kurmanji: مستأجرين الأرض؟
English Translation: Are you renting the land?
Kurmanji: لا والله، مو آجار، شراكة.
English Translation: No, it's not rent, it's a partnership.
Kurmanji: إيه نسبة يعني.
English Translation: A partnership?
English Translation: Yes, a percentage, I mean.
Kurmanji: حلو، هلق أنا اللي فهمته أهل خان طومان بريف حلب
الجنوبي مميزين بهالموضوع، وين ما راحوا عم يكونوا عم ياخذوا
أراضي شراكة أو عم يستأجروها.
English Translation: Nice. From what I understand, the
people of Khan Tuman in the southern countryside of Aleppo
are known for this. Wherever they go, they take land in
partnership or rent it.
Kurmanji: هلق شو زارعين حاليا؟
English Translation: Yes.
English Translation: What are you currently planting?
Kurmanji: خس.
English Translation: Lettuce.
Kurmanji: قد ايش زارعين إن شاء الله هيك بركة؟
English Translation: How much have you planted, God bless?
Kurmanji: والله تقريبا شي دونمين.
English Translation: Well, roughly about two dunams.
Kurmanji: دونمين، زارعين في أماكن تانية غير شي؟
English Translation: Two dunams. Have you planted in other
places besides here?
Kurmanji: لا.
English Translation: No.
Kurmanji: يعني قصدي إيش عم تزرعوا غير الخس؟ مو أنتم بس؟
English Translation: I mean, what else are you planting
besides lettuce? Not just you specifically?
Kurmanji: حبة سوداء، جلبان، عدس.
English Translation: Black cumin, peas, lentils.
Kurmanji: يعني هاي زراعة شتوية؟
English Translation: So this is winter farming?
Kurmanji: إيه، الخس هذا أخي تقريبا يعتبر ربيعي، يعني بداية
زراعته من شهر شباط.
English Translation: Yes. This lettuce, brother, is almost
considered a spring crop. I mean, its planting starts from
February.
Kurmanji: تمام، تمام، بالنص بالنص مع أهل الأرض، أصحاب الأرض؟
English Translation: Okay, okay. Is it fifty-fifty with the
people of the land, the landowners?
Kurmanji: لا مو نص بنص، خمسة وعشرين بالمية لأنه الكرم بده
ينفلح وكذا بتعرف أنت.
English Translation: No, it's not fifty-fifty, it's 25
percent, because the vineyard needs to be plowed and all,
you know.
Kurmanji: تمام، تمام، الله يعطيكم العافية.
English Translation: Okay, okay. May God give you health.
Kurmanji: عندكم حيوانات؟
English Translation: Do you have animals?
Kurmanji: إيه عندنا والله.
English Translation: Yes, we do indeed.
Kurmanji: إيش في عندكم؟
English Translation: What do you have?
Kurmanji: غنم، ماعز، وهيك، تربية.
English Translation: Sheep, goats, and such, for raising.
Kurmanji: قطعان ولا عدد قليل؟
English Translation: Flocks or a small number?
Kurmanji: لا لا، شغلة منيحة، يعني عشرة، خمسة عشر راس.
English Translation: No, no, a decent amount, meaning 10 or
15 heads.
Kurmanji: هلق عموما المهجرين هون، بفقيران، إيش بيشتغلوا؟ كيف
عايشين، خلينا نقرب شوي.
English Translation: Now generally, the displaced people
here in Faqiran, what do they work in? How are they living?
Let's get a bit closer.
Kurmanji: يعني تربية أغنام، اللي بشغلته العامل أو أخي مثلا ع
التالة، مع المنظمات غيره هيك ماشيين أمورهم.
English Translation: I mean, raising sheep. Those who work
as laborers, or brother, for example, on the hill, with
organizations and such, that's how they manage their
affairs.
Kurmanji: الأكثر، الأكثر بدي؟
English Translation: The majority, what about the majority?
Kurmanji: والله الأغلبية مزارعين.
English Translation: Well, the majority are farmers.
Kurmanji: الأغلبية مزارعين؟
English Translation: The majority are farmers?
Kurmanji: مهجرين اللي هون؟
English Translation: The displaced people who are here?
Kurmanji: إيه.
English Translation: Yes.
Kurmanji: ممتاز، يعني عم بيلاقوا فرص عمل خلينا نقول؟
English Translation: Excellent. So they are finding job
opportunities, let's say?
Kurmanji: فرص عمل وعم بيشتغلوا؟
English Translation: Job opportunities and they are working?
Kurmanji: إيه الحمد لله، الحمد لله.
English Translation: Yes, praise be to Allah, praise be to
Allah.
Kurmanji: يعني في أرض أخي، والواحد الإنسان أخي حسب صنعته، ما
بيعرف يشتغل غير هالشغلة، ما بيروح يشتغل مثلا أخي حدادة وكذا،
بده يشتغل بالأرض، ع موجب ما بيعرف بده يشتغل.
English Translation: Meaning, there is land, brother. And a
person, brother, depends on their profession. If they don't
know how to do anything else, they won't go work in
blacksmithing or something. They have to work in the land,
according to what they know how to do.
Kurmanji: الله يعطيكم العافية.
English Translation: May God give you health.
Kurmanji: والله يرزقكم يا رب.
English Translation: May God keep you safe.
English Translation: May God provide for you.
Kurmanji: شكرا إلك.
English Translation: May God keep you safe.
English Translation: Thank you.
Kurmanji: الله يعطيك العافية أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: May God give you health. Welcome.
Kurmanji: على الرغم من بساطة هالقرية وقلة عدد سكانها وعملهم
الزراعي لكن لا تخلو من وجود ورشة.
English Translation: Despite the simplicity of this village,
its small population, and their agricultural work, it is not
without a workshop.
Kurmanji: وهالورشة وحيدة لنجارة الموبيليا والعربي، النجارة
العربية.
English Translation: And this is the only workshop for
furniture and traditional carpentry, Arabic carpentry.
Kurmanji: رح نكون معكم بزيارة لهالورشة لنتعرف على وضعها
وعملها ونتعرف على صاحبها، ونشوف شو عم يشتغل اليوم بورشته،
تابعونا.
English Translation: We will take you on a visit to this
workshop to learn about its situation and work, and to meet
its owner, and see what he is working on today in his
workshop. Follow us.
Kurmanji: يا رب، السلام عليكم.
English Translation: Oh God. Peace be upon you.
Kurmanji: شلونك؟
English Translation: How are you?
Kurmanji: تمام، أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: Great, welcome.
Kurmanji: الله يعطيك العافية.
English Translation: May God give you health.
Kurmanji: الله يعافيك.
English Translation: May God give you health too.
Kurmanji: خلينا نتعرف عليك.
English Translation: Let's get to know you.
Kurmanji: مصطفى الجعفر، عيسى.
English Translation: Mustafa Al-Jaafar, Issa.
Kurmanji: أهلا وسهلا فيك.
English Translation: Welcome.
Kurmanji: الله يسلمك.
English Translation: May God keep you safe.
Kurmanji: شو هي الآلة؟
English Translation: What is this machine?
Kurmanji: هي ماكينة رابوب، بننظف الخشب.
English Translation: This is a thickness planer machine, we
clean the wood with it.
Kurmanji: رابوب تنظيف الخشب.
English Translation: A thickness planer for cleaning wood.
Kurmanji: نعم، الله يعطيكم العافية.
English Translation: Yes.
English Translation: Yes, may God give you health.
Kurmanji: الله يعافيك.
English Translation: May God give you health too.
Kurmanji: احكي لنا عن هالورشة.
English Translation: Tell us about this workshop.
Kurmanji: والله عندي خشب بشتغل، وميلامين بشتغل، بساوي مطابخ،
أبواب، ديكور بشتغل.
English Translation: Well, I work with wood, and I work with
melamine. I make kitchens, doors, and I do decor work.
Kurmanji: طيب، يعني هي الورشة شو تسمى؟
English Translation: Okay, so what is this workshop called?
Kurmanji: ورشة نجارة.
English Translation: A carpentry workshop.
Kurmanji: شو الآلات اللي هون؟
English Translation: What are the machines here?
Kurmanji: هون عندنا الماكينة هي الواح بنقص، عندنا المنشرة
بنقص الخشب.
English Translation: Here we have this machine, we cut
boards. We have the sawmill, we cut wood.
Kurmanji: إيش ما يكون خشب تخين بنقص.
English Translation: No matter how thick the wood is, we cut
it.
Kurmanji: يعني هي ورشة نجارة عربي وورشة نجارة موبيليا، إيش
كمان؟
English Translation: So this is a traditional carpentry
workshop and a furniture carpentry workshop. What else?
Kurmanji: موبيليا وعربي، إيه.
English Translation: Furniture and traditional, yes.
Kurmanji: تمام، وقلت لي غير الخشب إيش كمان عندك؟
English Translation: Okay. And you told me besides wood,
what else do you have?
Kurmanji: بي في سي، حرف تلبيس، حرف المطابخ.
English Translation: PVC, edge banding, for kitchen edges.
Kurmanji: تمام، هلق البضاعة اللي عم تشتغلها أنت هون، لوين
بتبيعها؟
English Translation: Okay. Now, the goods you are making
here, where do you sell them?
Kurmanji: زبون توصاية بيجينا.
English Translation: Customers place orders with us.
Kurmanji: لوين؟
English Translation: To where?
Kurmanji: على عفرين.
English Translation: To Afrin.
Kurmanji: كل عفرين.
English Translation: All of Afrin.
Kurmanji: إيه زبون توصاية.
English Translation: Yes, custom orders.
Kurmanji: هدول إيش هدول؟
English Translation: What are these?
Kurmanji: هذا تخت الخبز. بنطبخ عليها.
English Translation: This is a bread board. We cook on it.
Kurmanji: تخت الخبز؟
English Translation: A bread board?
Kurmanji: إيه.
English Translation: Yes.
Kurmanji: يعني شوبك ليكون قصدك؟ طاولة؟
English Translation: You mean a rolling pin? A table?
Kurmanji: إيه والطاولة، الطاولة، اللي فوق شو بصير، بيطبخوا
عليها.
English Translation: Yes, and the table. The table. The top
part, they cook on it.
Kurmanji: تمام، تمام، تمام.
English Translation: Okay, okay, okay.
Kurmanji: شقد صار لك بهاي الورشة؟
English Translation: How long have you been in this
workshop?
Kurmanji: صار لي ثلاث سنين فاتح هون.
English Translation: I've been open here for three years.
Kurmanji: إيه.
English Translation: Three years?
English Translation: Yes.
Kurmanji: قبل ما كان في ورشة هون؟
English Translation: Wasn't there a workshop here before?
Kurmanji: لا ما كان في، ما كان في ورشة على الخالص.
English Translation: No, there wasn't. There was absolutely
no workshop.
Kurmanji: ليش اخترت بدك تفتح الورشة بهاي الضيعة البسيطة
يعني؟
English Translation: Why did you choose to open the workshop
in this simple village?
Kurmanji: محلي أجار وجيت هون على الضيعة، قصدي محلي كان أجار
وما كان في شغل وجيت هون على الضيعة.
English Translation: My shop was rented, and I came here to
the village. I mean, my shop was rented and there was no
work, so I came here to the village.
Kurmanji: شلون بتأمن الكهرباء وشلون؟
English Translation: How do you secure electricity and such?
Kurmanji: عندي مولدة.
English Translation: I have a generator.
Kurmanji: مولدة؟
English Translation: A generator?
Kurmanji: مم.
English Translation: Mm-hmm.
Kurmanji: كم فرصة عمل بتأمن هالورشة؟
English Translation: How many job opportunities does this
workshop provide?
Kurmanji: مستحمل تسع معلمين.
English Translation: It supports nine skilled workers.
Kurmanji: تسعة، تسع معلمين.
English Translation: Nine, nine skilled workers.
Kurmanji: إيه.
English Translation: Yes.
Kurmanji: تمام، ما شاء الله عليكم.
English Translation: Okay, God bless you.
Kurmanji: بتداوم كم ساعة؟
English Translation: How many hours do you work?
Kurmanji: بنداوم ثمان ساعات.
English Translation: We work eight hours.
Kurmanji: ثمان ساعات.
English Translation: Eight hours.
Kurmanji: طيب في في سؤال عم يخطر على بالي ثاني، قديش هالمهنة
اليوم بتطعمي خبز خلينا نقول، قديش بتعيش؟
English Translation: Okay, there is another question that
comes to mind. How much does this profession put bread on
the table today, let's say? How much of a living does it
provide?
Kurmanji: مردودها شلون؟
English Translation: How is its return?
Kurmanji: مردود، يعني عندك إذا التسع عمال يشتغلوا عندك تسع
بيوت بتشتغل فيها ومقابيلها عندك تسع عمال بين إيديهم
بيشتغلوا.
English Translation: Return... I mean, if you have nine
workers working, you have nine households being supported by
it, and in addition to that, you have nine laborers working
under their supervision.
Kurmanji: صنايعية.
English Translation: Apprentices.
Kurmanji: يعني تسع معلمين وتسع صنايعية.
English Translation: Yes.
English Translation: So nine skilled workers and nine
apprentices.
Kurmanji: إيه.
English Translation: Yes.
Kurmanji: الله يعطيك العافية.
English Translation: May God give you health.
Kurmanji: الله يعافيك.
English Translation: May God give you health too.
Kurmanji: رح نشوف شو عم تشتغل.
English Translation: We will see what you are working on.
Kurmanji: يلا تفضل.
English Translation: Sure, go ahead.
Kurmanji: أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: Thank you.
English Translation: Welcome.
فقران كقرية عمرها أكبر من عمر السكان الحاليين الذين سكنوها
في أحسن تقدير قبل 400 عام.
Faqiran, as a village, is older than the current inhabitants
who settled it, at best estimation, 400 years ago.
حيث وجد في هذه القرية آبار رومانية عريقة، ربما يعود عمرها
إلى أكثر من 2000 سنة.
Ancient Roman wells were found in this village, which may
date back to more than 2,000 years.
للحديث عن تاريخ فقران يسرنا أن يكون معنا ضيفاً العم جعفر
عيسو جعفر، أحد أكبر الرجال المعمرين في القرية والعارف
بتاريخها.
To talk about the history of Faqiran, we are pleased to have
as our guest Uncle Jaafar Eiso Jaafar, one of the oldest men
in the village and knowledgeable about its history.
الله يعطيك العافية عمي أبو عيسو، شلونك؟
May God give you health, Uncle Abu Eiso. How are you?
أهليين شرفت، كيفك؟
Welcome, you've honored us. How are you?
الله يكرمك، احكيلي عن هالضيعة، خلينا نمشي هيك واحكيلي عن
هالضيعة.
May God bless you. Tell me about this village. Let's walk
like this and tell me about this village.
خيو هالضيعة، تاريخ الضيعة يعني ما هو مبينة، بس خط المي، خط
المي اللي جابوه من جوركان، سووا حووز بالحارة الفوقانية...
Brother, this village, the history of the village isn't
clear, but the water line, the water line they brought from
Jorkan, they made a reservoir in the upper neighborhood...
لقينا بجوا هالممر، ممر الحووز، أثر.
We found inside this passage, the reservoir passage, ruins.
أثر إيش؟ أثر قنوات رومانية، وقنوات فخار.
Ruins of what? Ruins of Roman canals, and pottery canals.
فحم ولا فخار؟
Charcoal or pottery?
فخار، فخار. قديمة. معناته أكثر من 400 سنة.
Pottery, pottery. Ancient. That means more than 400 years.
تمام، وفي عندكم جب روماني هون بعتقد بالوادي.
Right, and you have a Roman well here, I think in the
valley.
جب روماني كمان فيه. وفي الزيارة كمان، محل اللي عم بقول لك
عليه هلق نشوفه.
There's a Roman well too. And there's the shrine too, the
place I'm telling you about, we'll see it now.
في كمان يعني أثر مغارات كثيرة على بعضهم.
There are also ruins of many caves connected to each other.
على بعضهم، مفتوحات على بعض؟
Connected to each other, open to each other?
إي.
Yes.
هلق عرفنا إنه تاريخ هالقرية يعود للعهد الروماني، في آثار
رومانية.
Now we know that the history of this village dates back to
the Roman era, there are Roman ruins.
أكثر رومانية، أكبر رومانية.
Mostly Roman, the largest is Roman.
أكثر من رومان؟
More than Roman?
أكثر من رومان، من المغر، من المغر إي.
More than Roman, from the caves, from the caves, yes.
طيب في شيء بدك تضيفه؟
Okay, is there anything you want to add?
لا ما في شيء.
No, there's nothing.
طيب أنا بدي أسألك سؤال، الآن أنتم السكان الحاليين، اللي يعني
أنا حسب ما فهمت من 400 سنة وجيتوا لهون.
Alright, I want to ask you a question. Now, you current
residents, who, as I understand, came here 400 years ago.
أنتم كلكم إيزيديين.
You are all Yazidis.
إي نعم.
Yes.
من وين جيتوا؟
Where did you come from?
والله أنا بحسب أقوال اللي سمعت، نحن جايين من الشرق، بس من
وين جايين ما بعرف.
Well, according to what I've heard, we came from the east,
but from where exactly, I don't know.
من جزيرة، من صوب تركيا ما بعرف، بس اليزيدية كانوا هون، قبلنا
كانوا اليزيدية هون.
From Jazira, from the direction of Turkey, I don't know, but
the Yazidis were here, before us there were Yazidis here.
وين؟
Where?
هون بالقرى اللي حوالينا، المنطقة كلها يزيدية كانت.
Here in the villages around us. The whole region was Yazidi.
أنت تقصد حتى يعني جبل ليلون؟
You mean even Mount Laylun?
أيوة، وسهل الجوم.
Yes, and the Jowm plain.
سهل الجوم.
The Jowm plain.
كلهم يزيدية كانوا، جايين من الشرق. في ناس جايين من تركيا، في
ناس جايين من صوب عراق...
They were all Yazidis, coming from the east. There are
people coming from Turkey, there are people coming from the
direction of Iraq...
في ناس، اللي قبلنا ما نعرف من وين جايين.
There are people, those before us, we don't know where they
came from.
اللي كانوا بتركيا، اللي إجو من تركيا، هن إجو زمن الدولة
العثمانية لما كانت الحدود مفتوحة، الأراضي كلها معظمها...
Those who were in Turkey, who came from Turkey, they came
during the Ottoman Empire when the borders were open, the
lands were all mostly...
إي حدود كانت مفتوحة إي، الروحات والجيات، لأنه قرايبنا من
هونيك إجو لعنا.
Yes, the borders were open, yes, going back and forth,
because our relatives from there came to us.
طيب، خليني أسألك سؤال، العوائل اللي موجودة هون، مين هي
العوائل؟
Okay, let me ask you a question. The families that are here,
who are the families?
خيو عوائل بيت إسكانو، عائلة إسكانو، وبيت عيسو، بس كنية
الثنتين عيسو.
Brother, the families are the Iscano family, the Iscano
family, and the Eiso family, but the surname of both is
Eiso.
تمام، وأول عيلة كانت هون؟
Right, and the first family here?
أول عيلة بيت علولو.
The first family was the Aloulo family.
بيت علولو، أقدم عيلة من 400 سنة سكنوا هون.
The Aloulo family, the oldest family, lived here 400 years
ago.
إي إي، هن إجو، بعدين عيلتنا إجو بيت عيسو، بعدين بيت عيسو راح
جاب قرايبه بيت إسكانو.
Yes, yes, they came, then our family came, the Eiso family,
then the Eiso family went and brought their relatives, the
Iscano family.
واللي سكنوا بهالضيعة.
And they are the ones who lived in this village.
وبقيتوا هون.
And you stayed here.
وبقينا هون.
And we stayed here.
إلكن قرابات شي في القرى المجاورة؟
Do you have any relatives in the neighboring villages?
قرابة؟ قرابة نسوان.
Relatives? Relatives through marriage.
ما في قرابة عصبية؟
No blood relatives?
قرابة عصبية في بال... شو اسمه... هن إجو ثلاثة، واحد تم
بالجزيرة، وواحد بالمعراتة، وواحد إجا لهون.
Blood relatives, there are in... whatchamacallit... they
came as three, one stayed in Jazira, one in Ma'rata, and one
came here.
إلكن أقارب هنيك.
You have relatives there.
أقارب إي.
Relatives, yes.
طيب أنتو من أي عشيرة؟
Okay, what tribe are you from?
من عشيرة الشرقاوي.
From the Sharqawi tribe.
شرقاوي؟
Sharqawi?
الشرقي.
Sharqi.
الشرقي. هالعشيرة كردية أيزيدية؟
Sharqi. Is this tribe Kurdish Yazidi?
إيزيدية كردية.
Yazidi Kurdish.
احكيلي تاريخياً كيف كانت علاقتكم يعني مع الأكراد اللي هون
المسلمين أو مع العرب؟
Tell me historically, how was your relationship with the
Kurds here who are Muslims, or with the Arabs?
يا سيدي لهلق بالجزيرة في إلنا قرايب. ما كان يحس بحالهن
يزيدية، وعرب اللي حواليهن ما كان يحس حالهم عرب.
Sir, even now in Jazira we have relatives. They didn't feel
like they were Yazidis, and the Arabs around them didn't
feel like they were Arabs.
متفقين على بعضهم 100%، والمنطقة هون، منطقتنا هون بالأخص
قريتنا يعني قرية قره باش...
Getting along with each other 100%, and the region here, our
region here, especially our village, I mean the village of
Qarah Bash...
الأهل جولاقان، أهل كفر دلي، أهل ساتيان، أهل جوركان اللي
حوالينا.
The people of Julaqan, the people of Kafr Dali, the people
of Satyan, the people of Jorkan around us.
ما نحس بحالنا إذا دخلنا ببيت واحد، بيت إسلام، مدخلين على
بيتهم ما يفرقوا.
We wouldn't feel it if we entered someone's house, a Muslim
house, entering their house, there's no difference.
ما يفرق.
No difference.
وهن إذا دخلوا لعنا ما يفرقوا بأي شيء، بأي شيء.
And if they entered our house, there's no difference in
anything, in anything.
هلق أنت لما قلت قره باش، يعني هو الاسم التركي للقرية.
Now when you said Qarah Bash, that's the Turkish name for
the village.
القرية إيوا.
The village, yes.
اللي تعرب صار الرأس الأسود.
Which was Arabized to Ras Al-Aswad.
الرأس الأسود إيوا.
Ras Al-Aswad, yes.
والاسم الكردي هو؟
And the Kurdish name is?
فقيران.
Faqiran.
فقيران. طيب، في شغلة بدي أسألك إياها، لما أجدادكم إجوا سكنوا
هون من 400 سنة، كيف كانت هي المنطقة؟
Faqiran. Alright, there's something I want to ask you, when
your ancestors came and lived here 400 years ago, how was
this area?
إي والله ما بعرف كيف كانت يعني...
Well, honestly, I don't know how it was, I mean...
يعني كان فيها هالزيتون؟
I mean, did it have these olive trees?
لا، لا، لا، الزيتون ما كان فيه، كان في كروم. كان في كروم
عنب.
No, no, no, there were no olive trees, there were vineyards.
There were vineyards of grapes.
الزيتون فيه حوالي 200 سنة، يعني حوالي 200 سنة من زارعين
الزيتون.
Olives have been here for about 200 years, I mean they've
been planting olives for about 200 years.
طيب إيش كانوا يشتغلوا هن؟
Okay, what did they work in?
ها؟
Huh?
إيش كانوا يشتغلوا أجدادكم؟ غنامة؟
What did your ancestors work in? Sheep herding?
غنامة.
Sheep herding.
يلحقوا الغنم؟
Following the sheep?
يلحقوا الغنم، يمشوا ورا الماء وورا العشب.
Following the sheep, they walk after water and after grass.
يتبعوا الماء والعشب واستوطنوا هون.
They followed water and grass and settled here.
واستوطنوا هون.
And settled here.
وأول ما سكنوا سكنوا في المغر ولا سكنوا في، عمروا بيوت؟
And when they first lived, did they live in the caves or did
they build houses?
مغر، مغر. بعدين عمروا بيوت.
Caves, caves. Then they built houses.
ألف شكر عمي أبو عيسو.
A thousand thanks, Uncle Abu Eiso.
شكراً إلك، وشكراً إلك كمان أهلاً وسهلاً.
Thank you, and thank you too, welcome.
حياك الله.
God bless you.
أهلاً وسهلين بالإذاعة كمان حلب اليوم، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome to the Halab Today channel too, welcome.
حياك الله.
God bless you.
شكراً إلك، سلامات.
Thank you, goodbye.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
أهلاً.
Welcome.
شلونك؟
How are you?
شلون صحتك؟ الله يسلمك. كيفك؟
How is your health? May God keep you safe. How are you?
يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا رب.
May God give you health too.
حدا قلي إنه بيتكم هو أقدم بيت في الضيعة.
Someone told me that your house is the oldest house in the
village.
إي أهلاً وسهلاً، تفضل.
Yes, welcome, go ahead.
شرف، شرف معنا.
Please, please join us.
أهلاً وسهلاً، تفضل أهلاً.
Welcome, go ahead, welcome.
هاد هو؟
This is it?
إي هالبيت.
Yes, this house.
هاد، وهاد الاثنين؟
This one, and this one, both?
لا، هاد فرد بيت كله.
No, this is all a single house.
شرف، اطلع قدامنا.
Please, go ahead of us.
تفضل تفضل.
Go ahead, go ahead.
ولا عوافي.
Good health.
عمي هاد البيت ما تم ترميمه؟
Uncle, hasn't this house been restored?
ترميم يعني من أيمت من أول يعني هالبيوت قديماً هدول يعني.
Restoration, I mean, from when, from the beginning I mean,
these houses are ancient.
هيك شكله؟
It looks like this?
هيك شكله.
It looks like this.
فينا ندخل لجوا؟
Can we go inside?
يا أهلاً وسهلاً، تفضل.
Yes, welcome, go ahead.
شرف.
Please.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
يا رب.
Oh Lord.
هاد، هاد شكل البيت من جوا.
This, this is the shape of the house from the inside.
إي.
Yes.
بس كأنه مزرقينه من جوا؟
But it looks like you've plastered it from the inside?
إي مزرقينه، شمنتو زمانه شمنتو صار سوينا شمنتو.
Yes, plastered it. Cement, in its time there was cement, we
did cement.
بس كان هو بالأصل أقواس؟
But was it originally arches?
إي والله كان أول كله فرد شو اسمه، قطعنا من هون يعني كانت
نسوانا لحالها بتبرك هون شباب...
Yes, honestly, at first it was all a single whatchamacallit,
we partitioned it from here, I mean, our women would sit
alone here, the youth...
هاد البيت لأبوك ولا لجدك؟
Is this house your father's or your grandfather's?
لجدي وأبوي كان بيبرك فيه وأنا جيت قعدت فيه يعني.
For my grandfather, and my father used to stay in it, and I
came and lived in it.
هلق هي الصورة لمين وهي الصورة لمين؟
Now, whose picture is this and whose picture is this?
هذا جدي.
This is my grandfather.
شو اسمه؟
What is his name?
إبراهيم إسكانو عيسو.
Ibrahim Iscano Eiso.
وهاد والدك؟
And this is your father?
هذا أبوي إي.
This is my father, yes.
شو اسمه؟
What is his name?
الله يرحمهم، سعيد إبراهيم.
May God have mercy on them, Saeed Ibrahim.
سعيد إبراهيم.
Saeed Ibrahim.
إي.
Yes.
الله يرحم أمواتك. بيت كتير حلو، وهاد كلين مو هيك؟
May God have mercy on your dead. A very beautiful house. And
this is a "kaleen", right?
هذا كان أول بدال شو اسمه يعني.
This was at first instead of whatchamacallit, I mean.
هون، هون كلين.
Here, here is a kaleen.
إيوا.
Yes.
عرضه متر تقريباً.
Its width is about a meter.
إيوا، يعني إي إي مزبوط مزبوط.
Yes, I mean, yes, yes, exactly, exactly.
حلو كتير. هاد شو هاد؟
Very nice. What is this?
معليش، لو كنت فضولي شوي، هدول شو؟
Sorry, if I'm being a bit nosy, what are these?
هذا بالربيع بيطلعوا... وعم بيسووا بيحطوا بالخيط ويعني منظر
يعني.
This, in the spring they come out... and they make them, put
them on a string, and it's a decoration, I mean.
هاد مشان إيش؟
What is this for?
والله هاد منظر، مشان العين.
Honestly, this is a decoration, for the evil eye.
أنا بعرف هاد مشان ضد العين.
I know this is against the evil eye.
إيوا، إيوا مضبوط مضبوط.
Yes, yes, exactly, exactly.
شو اسمه، أوزليك شو اسمه؟
What is it called, "Uzerlik", what is it called?
أوزليك، أوزليك.
Uzerlik, uzerlik.
أوزليك.
Uzerlik.
أوزليك إيوا.
Uzerlik, yes.
يا سلام. بيت حلو كتير. خلينا نطلع شوي لبرا.
Wow. A very beautiful house. Let's go outside a bit.
يلا هلا.
Alright, come on.
هلق قبل كل شيء، هاد الوجوه هون، خلينا نشوف لفت نظري هي
الشغلة.
Now before anything else, these faces here, let's see, this
thing caught my attention.
هذا قناويش هاد؟
Are these "Qanawish"?
إي قناويش نحن عم نقول له.
Yes, we call it Qanawish.
أنتو بتشتغلوه هاد؟
Do you make this?
لا بيسووا، بيشتغلوا، كان بناتنا كانوا عم يسووهم.
No, they make it, they work on it, our daughters used to
make them.
من زمان ولا من هلق؟
From a long time ago or from now?
والله هي كان من زمان، هاد من 20 سنة 30 سنة يعني مو من هلق
يعني هاد.
Honestly, this was from a long time ago, this is from 20
years, 30 years, I mean it's not from now.
نعم.
Yes.
إي والله، بنات هالوقت ما بعرف بلكي يسووها.
Yes honestly, girls these days, I don't know, maybe they
make it.
في قبو تحت؟
Is there a basement underneath?
والله ما فيهم قبو، تحت ما في قبو.
Honestly, they don't have a basement, underneath there's no
basement.
ما في قبو.
There is no basement.
ما في قبو. بس فيها هي الغرفة هنيك إي، تحت شو اسمه، في أغراض
البيت يعني. تفضل تفضل من هون.
There is no basement. But it has this room there, yes, under
the whatchamacallit, there are household items. Please,
please, this way.
شرف، ما بيصير.
Please, I shouldn't.
خلينا نوقف هون بس.
Let's just stop here.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
ما شاء الله أنت باني البيت، والدك أو جدك الله يرحمه، بانيه
بشكل حلو إطلالة هيك على الغربي.
Mashallah, you built the house, your father or grandfather,
may God have mercy on him, built it beautifully with a view
looking west.
إيوا.
Yes.
بساتين الزيتون وقدامه الوادي. - مزبوط. - هذا شو هذا؟
Olive orchards and in front of it the valley. - Right. -
What is this?
هذا بالكردي نحن بنقول له شرك والله. - شو بتقولوا له؟ - شرك
شرك يعني...
In Kurdish, we call it "Şirik" to be honest. - What do you
call it? - "Şirik, şirik", meaning...
مشان مي، مجراب أيوة. - مزراب. - مزراب أيوة. - قديم كتير؟ -
إي قديم إي قديم.
For water, a spout, yes. - A spout. - A spout, yes. - Is it
very old? - Yes, it's old, yes, old.
هلق البيت عمره أكتر من 120 سنة، فأكيد بيكون يعني شكله هيك
حلو. - الله يعطيك العافية عمي أبو سعيد. - الله يعافيك، أهلاً
وسهلاً، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Now, the house is over 120 years old, so it definitely looks
nice like this. - God give you health, Uncle Abu Saeed. -
God give you health, welcome, welcome.
أتباع الديانة الإيزيدية إحدى مكونات الشعب السوري، ولكن هناك
جهل في فهم هذه المجموعة وهذه الديانة.
Followers of the Yazidi religion are one of the components
of the Syrian people, but there is ignorance in
understanding this group and this religion.
لمعرفة تفاصيل أكثر عن أتباع الديانة الإيزيدية، والذين هم
سكان قرية فقيران بالإجماع...
To find out more details about the followers of the Yazidi
religion, who make up the entire population of Faqiran
village...
...سيكون معنا ضيفاً الأستاذ ميرو ميرو، مختار قرية فقيران.
...we will have as our guest Mr. Miro Miro, the Mukhtar of
Faqiran village.
الله يعطيك العافية. - أهلاً وسهلاً أستاذ مصطفى. - شلونك
مختار؟ - سلامة. الله يعطيك العافية. أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم في
قرية فقيران.
God give you health. - Welcome, Mr. Mustafa. - How are you,
Mukhtar? - Well. God give you health. Welcome to Faqiran
village.
نحن ببلدنا. - الله يبارك فيك. - الله يكرمك. - احكي لي عن
الإيزيدية. - الإيزيدية ديانة قديمة...
We are in our own country. - God bless you. - God honor you.
- Tell me about Yazidism. - Yazidism is an ancient
religion...
...ترجع إلى سيدنا شيث عليه السلام، ابن آدم. لكن هناك خطأ
شائع حول الإيزيدية...
...that dates back to Prophet Seth, peace be upon him, the
son of Adam. But there is a common misconception about
Yazidism...
...على أساس أنه الإيزيدية كفرة. - إيزيدية أم يزيدية؟ -
الإيزيدية. - شو معناه الإيزيدي؟
...that basically says Yazidis are infidels. - Yazidi or
Yezidi? - Yazidi. - What does Yazidi mean?
الإيزيدي بمعنى عبدة الله، أو في منهم بيقولوا الإيزداهي.
الإيزداهي بالمعنى الحرفي "الذي خلقني"...
Yazidi means worshippers of God, or some say "Ezdahi".
Ezdahi literally means "the one who created me"...
...الذي هو رب العالمين. - الذي خلقني الذي هو رب العالمين. -
الذي هو رب العالمين.
...which is the Lord of the Worlds. - The one who created
me, which is the Lord of the Worlds. - Which is the Lord of
the Worlds.
الاعتقاد السائد لدى الآخرين على أنه الإيزيدية كفرة، فالشيء
الغلط...
The prevailing belief among others is that Yazidis are
infidels, which is wrong...
...أنه نحن دائماً وأبداً منذ بداية التكوين نحن بنعبد رب
العالمين. يعني قبل الأديان السماوية، أجدادنا بيعبدوا رب
العالمين.
...because we, always and forever, since the beginning of
creation, worship the Lord of the Worlds. Meaning, before
the Abrahamic religions, our ancestors worshipped the Lord
of the Worlds.
هو دين موحد. - هو دين موحد أكيد، ومؤمن بيوم الحساب...
It is a monotheistic religion. - It is definitely a
monotheistic religion, and believes in the Day of
Judgment...
...مؤمن بكافة الملائكة، بكافة الرسل والأنبياء اللي إجوا
لاحقاً. فموضوع اللي فيه...
...believes in all angels, in all messengers and prophets
who came later. So the issue in which there is...
...سوء فهم بالموضوع. الإيزيدية منتشرين بعراق، بسوريا،
بتركيا، بروسيا...
...a misunderstanding about the matter. Yazidis are spread
across Iraq, Syria, Turkey, Russia...
...وحالياً منتشرين بدول أوروبا، تقريباً فيني أقول لك معظم
دول أوروبا منتشرين. - طيب شو فلسفة يعني الديانة الإيزيدية؟
...and currently they are spread in European countries, I
can almost tell you they are spread in most European
countries. - Okay, what is the philosophy of the Yazidi
religion?
الفلسفة، مو موضوع، مو موضوع فلسفة، هو موضوع إيماني. الإيمان
بالإله الواحد...
The philosophy, it's not a matter, not a matter of
philosophy, it's a matter of faith. Belief in the One God...
...هو المعبود الواحد. - طيب. - نحن قناعتنا، كل من يعبد لغير
الله، أو يسجد لغير الله فهو كافر...
...He is the Only Worshipped. - Okay. - Our conviction is,
anyone who worships other than God, or prostrates to other
than God, is an infidel...
...نحن هيك بنعتقد. لذلك نحن بنقدس رئيس الملائكة اللي بنسميه
نحن طاووس الملائكة...
...that's what we believe. Therefore, we sanctify the
archangel, whom we call Tawûsê Melek (the Peacock Angel)...
...واللي باقي الأديان بتكفر فيه، لأنه نحن بالنسبة إلنا بنرفع
راسنا فيه كونه ما سجد لغير لله.
...and whom the other religions consider an infidel, because
for us, we hold our heads high for him since he did not
prostrate to anyone other than God.
فلما بيقولوا إنه ما سجد لآدم، مزبوط الحكي، نحن بنقول إنه
مزبوط الحكي، ما إنه خلاف...
So when they say that he did not prostrate to Adam, that's
correct, we say that this is correct, it's not a point of
dispute...
...لكن ما سجد لآدم هو نقطة فخر بالنسبة إلنا، لأنه ما سجد
لغير الإله الواحد، اللي هو خالق السماوات.
...but not prostrating to Adam is a point of pride for us,
because he did not prostrate to anyone other than the One
God, who is the Creator of the heavens.
بنسألكن من هو طاووس الملائكة؟ خلينا نمشي هيك شوي. - تمام. -
من هو طاووس الملائكة؟ - طاووس الملائكة حسب معتقداتنا...
We ask you, who is Tawûsê Melek? Let's walk a little bit. -
Alright. - Who is Tawûsê Melek? - Tawûsê Melek, according to
our beliefs...
...هو أول ملاك، ملاك خلقه رب العالمين، وما في بقعة بالأرض
إلا سجد فيها لله الواحد.
...is the first angel, an angel created by the Lord of the
Worlds, and there is no spot on earth where he hasn't
prostrated to the One God.
فهو كبير الملائكة... - إي هو، هو بالنسبة إلكم شو هو؟ -
بالنسبة إلنا، موضوع إيمان، فهمت علي؟ بنؤمن فيه.
So he is the greatest of angels... - Yes, he, what is he to
you? - For us, it's a matter of faith, you understand me? We
believe in him.
أنتم بتعبدوا الله يعني؟ - تمام. هو اللي إله فضل على جميع
البشر، لأنه حسب معتقداتنا هو اللي جمع تراب من أربع بقاع
الأرض لما عجنوا عجينة سيدنا آدم عليه السلام...
You worship God, then? - Exactly. He is the one who has
merit over all humanity, because according to our beliefs,
he is the one who gathered soil from the four corners of the
earth when they kneaded the clay of our master Adam, peace
be upon him...
...كون آدم عليه السلام مخلوق من تراب، فهو اللي كان مكلف بجمع
التراب من أربع زوايا الدنيا، نحن هيك بنعتقد.
...since Adam, peace be upon him, was created from dust, he
was the one tasked with gathering the soil from the four
corners of the world, that's what we believe.
طيب. - أنتم وين يعني في إلكن خلينا نقول مكان مقدس؟ - المكان
المقدس لكل الإيزيديين هو في جبل سنجار بـ لالش، معروف عنه
معبد لالش...
Okay. - Where do you have, let's say, a holy place? - The
holy place for all Yazidis is in Mount Sinjar in Lalish,
known as the Lalish Temple...
بالعراق؟ - بالعراق، تمام، محافظة الموصل. - موصل. - وحالياً
طبعاً بنتيجة المرض، كورونا، الطريق مقطوع ما حدا راح عالحج.
In Iraq? - In Iraq, exactly, Mosul Governorate. - Mosul. -
And currently, of course, due to the disease, Corona, the
road is cut off, no one went to pilgrimage.
ففي بعض الأحيان في، سابقا كانوا يروحوا سنويا يروحوا بـ شهر
نيسان...
So sometimes there is, previously they used to go annually,
they'd go in the month of April...
...أو بشهر تشرين الأول. - بيحجوا لهنيك؟ - أيوة، بيحجوا
لهنيك. - شو في هنيك؟ - هنيك في مزار قديم، بيتعبدوا فيه.
...or in the month of October. - Do they make a pilgrimage
there? - Yes, they make a pilgrimage there. - What is over
there? - There is an ancient shrine there, where they
worship.
شو اسمه هنيك المكان؟ - اسمه مزار لالش. - لالش. - ممم، ومعروف
لدى العراقيين أكثر من غير العرب، أو عندهم إلمام أكتر
بالموضوع.
What is the place called there? - It's called the Lalish
Shrine. - Lalish. - Mmhmm, and it is known among Iraqis more
than non-Arabs, or they have more knowledge about the
subject.
وشو، شو في هنيك، في نبع ماء مقدس كمان؟ - في نبع ماء مقدس،
نعم. - شو هو؟ - في، هو كمان بيسموه زمزم، زمزم...
And what, what is there, is there a holy water spring too? -
There is a holy water spring, yes. - What is it? - There is,
they also call it Zamzam, Zamzam...
الماء الأبيض، أو النبعة البيضاء، كمان بيسموه زمزم. - طيب. -
أنا سمعت إنه يعني في هناك سبعة ملائكة...
The white water, or the white spring, they also call it
Zamzam. - Okay. - I heard that, I mean, there are seven
angels...
...عند الإيزيدية، نعم... يعني بيشعلوا النار وبيدوروا حولها،
في سبع أشخاص بيدوروا حول النار كرمز للسبع ملائكة، شو القصة؟
...in Yazidism, yes... meaning they light a fire and circle
around it, there are seven people circling the fire as a
symbol for the seven angels, what is the story?
القصة، نحن حسب معتقداتنا أنه أيام الأسبوع سبعة، ففي كل يوم
من الأيام السبع مخلوق ملاك، وهو المسؤول عن هذا اليوم.
The story is, according to our beliefs, the days of the week
are seven, so on each of the seven days an angel is created,
and he is responsible for this day.
فهمت علي؟ نحن باعتقادنا إنه يوم السبت رب العالمين خلق الأرض،
أو الدنيا، ويوم الخميس أنهى، يوم الجمعة كانت عطلة.
Do you understand me? In our belief, on Saturday the Lord of
the Worlds created the earth, or the world, and on Thursday
He finished, Friday was a holiday.
فكل ملاك مختص بيوم من الأيام. - طيب، ولماذا يعني ليش النار
بالوسط؟ - النار بالوسط هو...
So each angel is dedicated to one of the days. - Okay, and
why, I mean, why is the fire in the middle? - The fire in
the middle is...
...يعني فينك تقول رمز للنور، وفينك تقول رمز للآخرة مشان
الواحد يحسب حسابه من جهنم. - طيب.
...I mean you could say it's a symbol of light, and you
could say it's a symbol for the afterlife so one takes heed
of Hell. - Okay.
بقي سؤال آخر، تفضل، أو أخير خلينا نقول. - تفضل. - حسب
معلوماتي أيضاً إنه أنتم بتصلوا...
One other question remains, go ahead, or let's say the last
one. - Go ahead. - According to my information as well, you
pray...
...باتجاه الشمس، صباحاً يعني باتجاه الشرق. - تمام. - مساءً
باتجاه الغرب، وظهراً باتجاه الجنوب. شو القصة؟
...towards the sun, in the morning meaning towards the east.
- Correct. - In the evening towards the west, and at noon
towards the south. What's the story?
القصة، شو العلاقة بينكم وبين الشمس؟ - تمام. الشمس هو نور لرب
العالمين نحن بنعتبره. لولا الشمس لما اخضرت الأرض...
The story, what is the relationship between you and the sun?
- Right. The sun is a light from the Lord of the Worlds, we
consider it. Without the sun, the earth wouldn't be green...
...كلياتنا بنعرف عملية اليخضور بتصير بوجود الشمس. فلولا
الشمس لما كانت الحياة عالأرض، ما كانت الحياة عالأرض.
...we all know the process of chlorophyll happens in the
presence of the sun. So without the sun, there would be no
life on earth, there would be no life on earth.
الشمس هو سبب الحياة، سبب وجود النبات، سبب تنفس البشر...
The sun is the cause of life, the cause of the existence of
plants, the cause of humans breathing...
...سبب تقوية عظام الإنسان، فالشمس إله بركات عند رب العالمين،
أو نور من عند رب العالمين. فلذلك نحن مو موضوع إنه عبادة شمس،
لأ.
...the cause of strengthening human bones, so the sun has
blessings from the Lord of the Worlds, or is a light from
the Lord of the Worlds. Therefore, for us, it's not a matter
of worshipping the sun, no.
لأن هلا كل إخواننا المسلمين بيتجهوا عالكعبة، فهن بيعبدوا
الكعبة؟ - أنا قلت أنا قلت أنتم تتجهوا باتجاه الشمس. - صح.
Because now all our Muslim brothers turn towards the Kaaba,
does that mean they worship the Kaaba? - I said, I said you
turn towards the sun. - Right.
أنا ما قلت أنتم بتعبدوا الشمس. - تمام، تمام. - طيب، في سؤال
آخر، تفضل. شقد أعداد الإيزيديين بسوريا ووين توزعهم الجغرافي؟
I didn't say you worship the sun. - Right, right. - Okay,
there is another question, go ahead. What is the number of
Yazidis in Syria and where is their geographical
distribution?
هلا توزعهم الجغرافي، في بمحافظة حسكة، وفي بمحافظة حلب. هدول
المركزين الأساسيين أو المحافظتين الأساسيات بالنسبة لسوريا.
Now, their geographical distribution, there are some in the
Al-Hasakah governorate, and in the Aleppo governorate. These
are the two main centers or the two main governorates for
Syria.
والأعداد؟ - الأعداد حالياً غير مستقرة بسبب الهجرة. - تقريبية
يعني بالأصل والآن؟
And the numbers? - The numbers currently are unstable due to
migration. - Approximately, I mean originally and now?
تقريبية حالياً هلا بعفرين ما بقيان حدا، 19، 20 قرية إيزيدية
ما بقيان فيه بحدود 3000 بني آدم، 3500 بني آدم. - وبالحسكة؟
Approximately currently in Afrin there's hardly anyone left,
19, 20 Yazidi villages, there's only about 3000 people, 3500
people left. - And in Al-Hasakah?
والله الحسكة ما عندي علم. - طيب، سابقاً قديش كان أعدادهم؟ -
عدد الـ... فينك تضربه بخمسة أضعاف. - تمام.
Honestly, Al-Hasakah, I have no knowledge. - Okay,
previously what was their number? - The number of... you can
multiply it by five times. - Okay.
لأنه، أوضاع غير مستقرة، فلذلك في هجرة. هو سابقاً نحن في
عندنا هجرة...
Because, the situations are unstable, so there is migration.
In the past, we also had migration...
إيمتى أقدم هجرة إلكم؟ - والله أنا بعرف من عام 1960 تقريباً
في هجرة لأوروبا، لكن كان بسبب الدراسة، بسبب أحوال مادية، لكن
حالياً بسبب الأحوال الأمنية...
When was your oldest migration? - Well, I know since around
1960 there was migration to Europe, but it was because of
studies, because of financial conditions, but currently
because of security conditions...
...في هجرة أكتر. - تمام. - الله يعطيك العافية. - أهلاً
وسهلاً بيك أستاذ مصطفى. - شكراً إلك أستاذ ميرو. - الله
يسلمك. أهلاً بك.
...there is more migration. - Alright. - God give you
health. - Welcome to you, Mr. Mustafa. - Thank you, Mr.
Miro. - God keep you safe. Welcome.
بهالفقرة الصغيرة رح نحاول نجول معكم بالسيارة، في قلب قرية
فقيران. نشوف معالمها، وطبيعتها الحلوة.
In this short segment, we will try to take a tour with you
by car, in the heart of Faqiran village. To see its
landmarks, and its beautiful nature.
هلا واضح من هون إنه هي مبنية على السفح الجنوبي لهضبة
جبلية...
Now it's clear from here that it's built on the southern
slope of a mountainous plateau...
طبعاً الهضبة الجبلية يعني موجودة غرب مدينة عفرين.
Of course, the mountainous plateau is, I mean, located west
of the city of Afrin.
رح ندخل هلا في الطريق يلي بيعبر من جنوبها، ونلتف حولها
باتجاه الشمال وبعدين ندخل معكم لقلب الضيعة.
We will enter now on the road that crosses from its south,
and wrap around it towards the north and then enter with you
into the heart of the village.
بدأت معالم الضيعة تظهر. بيوت الضيعة عاليمين، وعاليسار البيدر
والمدرسة الوحيدة اللي هي المدرسة الابتدائية الموجودة في
القرية.
The village's landmarks started to appear. The village's
houses on the right, and on the left is the threshing floor
and the only school, which is the primary school located in
the village.
أيضاً على يسارنا، وقبل المقبرة، في بيدر آخر، في مهجرين من
ريف حلب الجنوبي...
Also on our left, and before the cemetery, there is another
threshing floor, there are displaced people from the
southern countryside of Aleppo...
...نازلين فيه وبانيين خيامهم. هون على يسارنا الزيارة
الواضحة...
...staying there and have pitched their tents. Here on our
left is the clearly visible shrine...
...وأمامنا الآن الوادي اللي بيمر غرب جنوب القرية. وهي معصرة
قديمة هون، قديمة كتير...
...and in front of us now is the valley that passes west-
south of the village. And this is an old press here, very
old...
...يمكن عمرها حوالي...
...maybe its age is around...
أكثر من 100 سنة.
More than 100 years.
هذا هو الوادي.
This is the valley.
أيضاً أمامنا في معلم من معالم فقيران المميزة واللي هي شجرة
البلوط.
Also in front of us, there is one of the distinct landmarks
of Faqiran, which is the oak tree.
كانت الناس وخاصة الأطفال من هذه القرية يتمرجحوا بهالشجرة
الكبيرة...
The people, and especially the children from this village,
used to swing on this big tree...
...في المناسبات، ويمكن يبركوا وينبسطوا، يتغدوا، يفرحوا
تحتها.
...during occasions, and maybe they would sit, enjoy, have
lunch, and rejoice under it.
معلم كتير حلو.
A very beautiful landmark.
الضيعة صغيرة كتير، وطبيعتها يعني مبنية فوق هضبة قاسية
حقيقةً.
The village is very small, and its nature, meaning it is
built on a really harsh hill.
الطابع الزراعي واضح تماماً على القرية.
The agricultural character is quite clear in the village.
لاحظوا أكوام أغصان الزيتون اليابس.
Notice the piles of dry olive branches.
هي عبارة عن قاسم مشترك بين كل يعني أسوار بيوت القرية.
They are a common denominator among all, I mean, the walls
of the houses in the village.
السبب إنه عندما يتم كسح أشجار الزيتون، تقليمها...
The reason is that when olive trees are pruned, trimmed...
...يعني تقليمها سنوياً أو كل سنتين مرة.
...I mean trimmed annually or once every two years.
يتم الاستفادة من أغصان الزيتون اليابس.
The dry olive branches are utilized.
كسور توضع على حيطان البيوت من أجل الاستفادة منها في الشتوية.
As a fence placed on the walls of the houses in order to
benefit from them in the winter.
في التدفئة أو في الطبخ عليها، استعمالها كوقود طيلة فصول
السنة.
For heating or cooking on them, using them as fuel
throughout the seasons of the year.
تقريباً وصلنا لأعلى مكان في القرية.
We have almost reached the highest place in the village.
هالمكان قديم، مميز.
This place is old and distinct.
هذا هو الآن الخزان.
This is the reservoir now.
خزان تسقى منه القرية قديماً وإلى الآن.
A reservoir from which the village was supplied with water
in the past and until now.
هون مكان قديم.
Here is an old place.
هون كان في زيارة، متل ما انكم شايفين في جرنين قديمين من
البازلت الأسود.
Here there was a shrine, as you can see, there are two old
basins of black basalt.
كان في زيارة هون، كان سكان القرية يعني يطلعوا لهون، يتبركوا
فيها أحياناً.
There was a shrine here, the residents of the village used
to come up here to be blessed by it sometimes.
حسب ما يعني علمنا.
According to what we have learned.
أيضاً هون مكان منبسط يعني في أعلى القرية شبيه بالبيدر.
Also here is a flat place, I mean at the top of the village,
similar to a threshing floor.
الناس ترعى فيها يعني حيواناتها.
People graze their animals in it.
لاحظوا الشيء المميز، كيف يتم صنع جدار من أغصان الأشجار
المقلمة أمام البيوت.
Notice the distinct thing, how a wall is made from the
branches of the pruned trees in front of the houses.
وتزرع داخلها حواكير.
And small gardens are planted inside them.
على يميننا أشجار اللوز المثمرة والتفاح.
On our right are the fruitful almond trees and apples.
طبيعة خلابة حقيقةً.
A truly picturesque nature.
الآن أمامنا انفتح المشهد على منصة أو على مسرح...
Now in front of us, the scene has opened up to a platform or
a stage...
...حلو جداً جداً من الطبيعة.
...a very, very beautiful one of nature.
لاحظوا عشرات آلاف أشجار الزيتون.
Notice the tens of thousands of olive trees.
نحن الآن نطل على جنوب القرية.
We are now looking over the south of the village.
كل هذه البساتين اللي أمامنا هي تعود للقرية...
All these orchards in front of us belong to the village...
...حتى تصل البساتين إلى طريق جنديرس، عفرين.
...until the orchards reach the road to Jinderes, Afrin.
هلق رح نختم، بس قبل ما نختم رح نقول كلمتين.
Now we are going to conclude, but before we conclude, we
will say a few words.
هالكلمتين هني إنه نحن استمتعنا معكم بهالجولة، بقرية فقيران
بريف عفرين الغربي.
These words are that we enjoyed this tour with you, in the
village of Faqiran in the western countryside of Afrin.
أجمل ما تعرفنا عليه هو طبيعة أهل هالقرية البسيطين والطيبين
كتير...
The most beautiful thing we got to know is the nature of the
people of this village, who are simple and very kind...
...وطبيعتهم الزراعية.
...and their agricultural nature.
وأيضاً اكتشفنا معكم ولأول مرة ماهية الديانة الإيزيدية، ديانة
أهل هالقرية.
And we also discovered with you, for the first time, what
the Yazidi religion is, the religion of the people of this
village.
وأيضاً تعرفنا على نمط حياة الأهالي وللمهجرين لهون.
And we also learned about the lifestyle of the locals and
the displaced people here.
نوعدكم إنه نكون معكم في الأسابيع القادمة، بجولات جديدة من
مناطق أيضاً حلوة كتير من سوريا الحبيبة.
We promise you that we will be with you in the coming weeks,
with new tours from also very beautiful areas of beloved
Syria.
لمتابعة برنامجنا، تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة.
To follow our program, follow the Facebook page of the
channel.
وأيضاً موقعنا على الإنترنت halabtodaytv.net
And also our website halabtodaytv.net
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.